A Finding Aid to the Mel Ramos Papers, 1959-1984, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Mel Ramos papers
1959-1984
Archives of American Art
Ramos, Mel, 1935-2018
AAA.ramomel
Archival Resource Key
0.6 Linear feet
The papers of California pop artist and teacher Mel Ramos measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1959 to 1984. The collection documents Ramos's career as an artist through correspondence with Lawrence Alloway, Dwan Gallery, Roy Lichtenstein, David Stuart, and Tom Wesselman, among others; a few inventories, invoices, and loan agreements; documentation of his work with the San Francisco Art Institute; and exhibition announcements and catalogs. Writings include two manuscripts on Ramos and the Pop Art movement, a one-page interview of Ramos, and poetry by Robin Skelton. Of interest in the collection, are files containing photographs, photo-collages, and clippings used for paintings such as "Elephant Seal," "Virnaburger," and "Manet's Olympia."
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection, the papers are arranged as one series.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is available on microfilm reels 3652-3653 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Mel Ramos in July 1985.
Related Materials
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an interview of Mel Ramos conducted on May 15, 1981, by Paul Karlstrom.
Biographical / Historical
Mel Ramos (1935-2018), born Melvin John Ramos, was a painter, pop artist, and teacher in California. Ramos was born in Sacramento, California. In 1955 he married Leta Helmers, who served as a model for many of his early paintings. Ramos received his M.A. from Sacramento State College in 1958 and taught a Mira Loma High School. In 1963 his work was included in Six More, a major exhibition of Pop Art at the Los Angeles County Museum. One year later he had his first solo show in New York at Bianchini Gallery. In 1965, he began showing his art at David Stuart Gallery in Los Angeles. Ramos also had a long career (1966-1997) as a professor at California State University, East Bay.
Scope and Contents
The papers of California pop artist and teacher Mel Ramos measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1959 to 1984. The collection documents Ramos's career as an artist through correspondence with Lawrence Alloway, Dwan Gallery, Roy Lichtenstein, David Stuart, and Tom Wesselman, among others; a few inventories, invoices, and loan agreements; documentation of his work with the San Francisco Art Institute; and exhibition announcements and catalogs. Writings include two manuscripts on Ramos and the Pop Art movement, a one-page interview of Ramos, and poetry by Robin Skelton. Of interest in the collection, are files containing photographs, photo-collages, and clippings used for paintings such as "Elephant Seal," "Virnaburger," and "Manet's Olympia."
Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- California; Pop art; Painters -- California -- Oakland; Hispanic American artists; Works of art; Interviews; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997; Alloway, Lawrence, 1926-1990; Wesselmann, Tom, 1931-2004; Thiebaud, Wayne
- Mel Ramos Papers, 1959-1984; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  The papers of California pop artist and teacher Mel Ramos measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1959 to 1984. The collection documents Ramos's career as an artist through correspondence with Lawrence Alloway, Dwan Gallery, Roy Lichtenstein, David Stuart, and Tom Wesselman, among others; a few inventories, invoices, and loan agreements; documentation of his work with the San Francisco Art Institute; and exhibition announcements and catalogs. Writings include two manuscripts on Ramos and the Pop Art movement, a one-page interview of Ramos, and poetry by Robin Skelton. Of interest in the collection, are files containing photographs, photo-collages, and clippings used for paintings such as "Elephant Seal," "Virnaburger," and "Manet's Olympia."
  - Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1963 January-May; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1963 June-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1964 January-June; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1964 July-November; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1964 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1965 January; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1965 February; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1965 February; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1965 March-May; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1965 June-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Correspondence, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Correspondence, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Correspondence, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
  - Correspondence, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-29)
  - Correspondence, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
  - Correspondence, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34-36)
  - Loan Agreements and Inventory of Artwork, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Receipts and Invoices, circa 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Business Records, Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - San Francisco Art Institute, 1966-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subject File, "Francois Gerard - Cupid & Psyche", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Subject File, "Botticelli - Venus", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subject File, "Boucher - Miss O'Murphy", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subject File, "J. L. David - L'Amour et Psyche", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Subject File, "Elephant Seal", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subject File, "Ingres - Le Grande Odalisque", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Subject File, "Manet's Olympia", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subject File, "Modigliani Nudo Coricato Alla Modigliani", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subject File, "Navajo - Nudo", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Subject File, "Picot's L'Amor et Psyche", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Subject File, "Speiser Commission", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Subject File, "Velasquez - Rokeby", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Subject File, "Virnaburger", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified Source Material, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Artwork, "Study for Salami/Modigliani #4", circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Writings, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1960s-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1968, 1980, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Printed Material, Miscellaneous, circa 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)